Guide to the Dan Beach Bradley and Cornelius Beach Bradley Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Dan Beach and Cornelius Beach Bradley papers
1801-1921
MS 97
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
Professional papers of Dan Beach Bradley and his son, Cornelius Beach Bradley, both missionaries to Thailand (then Siam) in the nineteenth century. The papers of Dan Beach Bradley consist of four manuscript volumes of a Siamo-English dictionary, articles and notes on the history and culture of Siam, including a list (copy) by the king of Siam of his 61 children in 1852, as well as copies of essays on the Siamese language in both English and Siamese by the king. A number of unidentified papers in Siamese, collected by Dan B. Bradley, are also included. His personal papers which contain 28 volumes of his journals (ca. 1835-1873), are in the library of Oberlin College. The journals have been filmed. Several maps of Thailand and China (1867-1870) have been sent to the Map Department of the Yale University Library. The Cornelius Beach Bradley papers consist chiefly of manuscripts on the Siamese language and rubbings of inscriptions on stone tablets accompanied by correspondence and notes on their translation. Other reprints relate to the origin of Siamese alphabetic writing and an analysis of the language. There is a small amount of correspondence for both Dan Beach and Cornelius Beach Bradley and one letter from Dan Beach Bradley (1767-1838) to his sister, Mehetabel, dated August 23, 1801.
Bradley, Dan Beach, 1804-1873
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Harold C. Bradley, 1959.
Biographical / Historical
Dan Beach Bradley (1804-1873): missionary to Thailand; compiler of a Siamese-English dictionary.Cornelius Beach Bradley (1843-1936): missionary to Thailand. 1871-1874; professor at University of California at Berkeley, 1882-1911.
Scope and Contents
Professional papers of Dan Beach Bradley and his son, Cornelius Beach Bradley, both missionaries to Thailand (then Siam) in the nineteenth century. The papers of Dan Beach Bradley consist of four manuscript volumes of a Siamo-English dictionary, articles and notes on the history and culture of Siam, including a list (copy) by the king of Siam of his 61 children in 1852, as well as copies of essays on the Siamese language in both English and Siamese by the king. A number of unidentified papers in Siamese, collected by Dan B. Bradley, are also included. His personal papers which contain 28 volumes of his journals (ca. 1835-1873), are in the library of Oberlin College. The journals have been filmed. Several maps of Thailand and China (1867-1870) have been sent to the Map Department of the Yale University Library. The Cornelius Beach Bradley papers consist chiefly of manuscripts on the Siamese language and rubbings of inscriptions on stone tablets accompanied by correspondence and notes on their translation. Other reprints relate to the origin of Siamese alphabetic writing and an analysis of the language. There is a small amount of correspondence for both Dan Beach and Cornelius Beach Bradley and one letter from Dan Beach Bradley (1767-1838) to his sister, Mehetabel, dated August 23, 1801.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 274 instead of the originals.
Linguistics; Missions -- Thailand; Paleography, Thai; Thai language; Southeast Asia -- Description and travel; Thailand -- Description and travel; Thailand -- History -- 1782-1945; Missionaries; Bradley, Cornelius Beach, 1843-1936; Bradley, Dan Beach, 1804-1873; Bradley, Dan, 1767-1838
- Inventory
  - ALS to Mehetabel (Bradley Bellamy) from her brother Dan Bradley (1767-1838), 1801 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Correspondence of Dan Beach Bradley (1804-1873), 1848-1863 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Correspondence of Cornelius Beach Bradley, 1915-1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
  - Receipts of Dr. Dan Beach Bradley (1804-1873), 1848-1865 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - Siamo-English dictionary. Vol. I, undated (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Siamo-English dictionary. Vol. II, undated (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Siamo-English dictionary. Vol. III, undated (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
  - Siamo-English dictionary. Vol. IV, undated (Box 2, Folder 8, Reel 2U)
  - Psalms in Siamese, undated (Box 2, Folder 9, Reel 2U)
  - Two manuscripts [by Cornelius Beach Bradley?] concerning various aspects of the Siamese language, undated (Box 2, Folder 10, Reel 2U)
  - "The Siamese Vowels and Diphthongs," by Cornelius Beach Bradley, 1902 December 28 (Box 2, Folder 11, Reel 2U)
  - "Scheme for the Sequence of Words in a Siamese Vocabulary," by Cornelius Beach Bradley, undated (Box 2, Folder 12, Reel 2U)
  - "Indication of a Consonant-Shift in Siamese Since the Introduction of Alphabetical Writing" [reprint by Cornelius Beach Bradley], 1908 (Box 2, Folder 13, Reel 2U)
  - "The Proximate Source of the Siamese Alphabet" [reprint by Cornelius Beach Bradley], 1912 (Box 2, Folder 13, Reel 2U)
  - "The Siamese Vocabulary: Its Formal and Conceptual Features," by Cornelius Beach Bradley, undated (Box 2, Folder 14, Reel 2U)
  - "The Tone Accents of Two Chinese Dialects," by [Cornelius Beach Bradley], 1914 November 27 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - "The Phyllotaxy of Phoenix Canariensis," by Cornelius Beach Bradley, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - "Taxonomy, or the Geometry of Leaf-Arrangement," by Cornelius Beach Bradley, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Correspondence, photographs, and tracings of the inscriptions from Chayā, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 17, Reel 3U)
  - Reprints, transcripts, and transliteration by Cornelius Beach Bradley of the Sukhōthai inscription of Rām Khamhêng, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 18, Reel 3U)
  - "The History of the Sukhōthai Letters," by Cornelius Beach Bradley, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 19, Reel 3U)
  - "Graphic Analysis of the Tone-accents of the Siamese language," by Cornelius Beach Bradley, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 20, Reel 3U)
  - Miscellaneous research and data notes by Cornelius Beach Bradley, [ca. 1903] (Box 3, Folder 21, Reel 3U)
  - "A Book Publishing & Illustrating the evils of Opium...," by Dan Beach Bradley, 1841 January 9 (Box 3, Folder 22, Reel 3U)
  - "New Laws Concerning Business Transacted on Water and Land in Siam," by [Dan Beach Bradley], undated (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Notes by [Dan Beach Bradley]: "Notes on Siamese Manners and Customs," "The Kingdom of Siam," and a "Synopsis of Siamese History", undated (Box 3, Folder 24, Reel 3U)
  - Notes of Dan Beach Bradley pertaining to the Kingdom and King of Siam, 1852-1863 (Box 3, Folder 25, Reel 3U)
  - Miscellaneous notes of Dan Beach Bradley pertaining to the Siamese language and Siamese books in the mission library, undated (Box 3, Folder 26, Reel 3U)
  - Unidentified notes and documents in Siamese either written or collected by Cornelius Beach and Dan Beach Bradley, undated (Box 3, Folder 27, Reel 3U)
  - Recipe for making wood oil and varnish and a recipe for a pain killer [written by Dan Beach Bradley?], undated (Box 3, Folder 28, Reel 3U)
  - Issue of the Bangkok Times, 1919 November 6 (Box 3, Folder 29, Reel 3U)
  - Issue of the Bangkok Recorder, 1865 November 3 (Box 3, Folder 29, Reel 3U)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 30, Reel 3U)
  - Note cards of Siamese words, undated (Box 3, Folder 31, Reel 3U)
  - Tables for article on a Russian method of multiplication, undated (Box 3, Folder 32, Reel 3U)
  - From the papers of Cornelius Beach Bradley
    - Inscriptions from Wat Prasat and Wat Chieng Man, including photographs, transcriptions, transliterations and translations, undated (Box 4, Reel 3U)
    - Transliteration in modern Siamese letters of the four Sukhōthai inscriptions, following the original of Ram Khamkang, including photographs of the stone tablets, undated (Box 4, Reel 3U)
    - Studies of nothern [sic] writings, including rubbings, transcriptions, correspondence and photograph of a tablet, 1903-1914 (Box 4, Reel 3U)
    - Pencil sketch, undated (Box 4, Reel 3U)
    - Tones of Cantonese [diagram]; Seven Test-Letters [chart]; correspondence; rubbings; unidentified materials, undated (Box 5, Reel 3U)